<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <info><title>TASUB: The Triple Axis Calculation Module</title><author>
            <personname>Mark Koennecke</personname>
        </author>
        <date/>
    </info>
    <sect1>
        <title>TASUB: The Triple Axis Calculation Module</title>
        <para>On a triple axis instrument the parameters incoming energy, Q-position in 3D and
            analyzed energy have to be changed frequently. These calculations are the task of the
            TASUB module. This module uses the calculus described by M. Lumsden, J. L. Roberston and
            M. Yethiraj in J. Appl. Cryst. (2005), 38, 405-411. The special feauture of this
            algorithm is that the tilt cradles of the sample table are used to help during alignment
            and in order to drive out of plane (within the limits of the tilt cradles). For
            alignment, two reflections must be located and their angles and Q-E parameters entered
            into the module. Then a UB matrix can be calculated. With a UB matrix, the Q-E variables
            ei, ki, ef, kf, en, qh, qk and ql can be driven as virtual motors in SICS. </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Commands understood by Tasub</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Monochromator and Analyzer Parameters</title>
            <para>Incident and scattered energies are defined by monochromator crystals. In order
                for the calculations to work, some parameters need to be configured. Monochromator
                and analyzer parameters can be accessed with the prefixes: The parameter syntax used
                is as usual: giving only the parameter name queries the value, giving the parameter
                plus a value sets the parameter to the new value. The following parameters are
                supported: </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>tasub mono</command>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Monochromator properties </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>tasub ana</command>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Analyser properties </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>Allowed <command>properties </command> for <command>tasub mono</command> and
                    <command>tasub ana</command> one of:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>dd</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The d-spacing of the reflection used </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>ss</command>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The scattering sense, 1 or -1 are possible. </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>hb1</command>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>First parameter for the calculation of the horizontal curvature
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>hb2 </command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Second parameter for the calculation of the horizontal curvature
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>vb1</command>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>First parameter for the calculation of the vertical curvature </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>vb2</command>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Second parameter for the calculation of the vertical curvature </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>Examples: </para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>tasub mono dd </command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>will print the current d-spacing of the monochromator </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>tasub mono dd </command><replaceable>4.3</replaceable>
                    </term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Will set the d-spacing of the monochromator to 4.3 </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>tasub mono ss </command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>will print the scattering sense of the monochromator </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>tasub ana ss </command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>will print the scattering sense of the analyser </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>tasub ana ss 1</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>will set the scattering sense of the analyser to 1</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Cell Parameters</title>
            <para> In order for the UB matrix calculation to work, the cell constants must be known: <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub cell </command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This command prints the current cell parameters. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub cell </command><replaceable>a b c alpha beta
                            gamma</replaceable>
                        </term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This command sets the new cell parameters. All six values must be
                                given. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist></para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Reflection Management</title>
            <para> In order to calculate a UB matrix a list of reflections must be maintained. This
                is done with the commands in this section: <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub clear </command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Clears the reflection list </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub listref</command>
                        </term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Prints a list of all known reflections. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub del </command><replaceable>num</replaceable>
                        </term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Delete the reflection number num from the list </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub addref </command><replaceable>qh qk ql </replaceable></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Adds a reflection to the list. The indices of the reflections are
                                given. The angles and energy values are read from the motors. Use
                                this command only when the instrument is positioned right on a
                                reflection. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub addref </command><replaceable>qh qk ql a3 a4 sgu sgl ei
                                ef </replaceable></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Add a new reflection to the list. Besides the indices all angles
                                are given: a3, the sample rotation, a4, sample two theta, sgu, upper
                                tilt cradle, sgl, lower tilt cradle and incoming energey ei and
                                outgoing energy ef. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub addauxref </command><replaceable>qh qk ql
                            </replaceable></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Adds an auxiliary reflection with indices qh, qk, ql to the list.
                                A4 is calculated from cell constants. A3 is either left alone or is
                                calculated to have the correct angular difference to a previous
                                reflection. This is a help for setting up the instrument or running
                                powder mode. When a UB has been generated from auxiliary
                                reflections, a3, sgu and sgl angles will be incorrect. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub repref </command><replaceable>id qh qk ql a3 a4 sgu sgl
                                ei ef </replaceable></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Modifies the reflection with id id to have the values given.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist></para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Calculations</title>
            <para> This section covers the parameters and commands to use to make the module do
                calculations for you. <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasbub const ki | kf | elastic </command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Sets a parameter to determine if KI or KF is fixed when the energy
                                transfer en is being driven. Allowed values: ki, kf, elastic. In
                                elastic mode the analyzer is disregarded. This is useful for two
                                circle diffractometers. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub const </command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Prints if ki or kf is fixed. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub ss </command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Prints the sample scattering sense. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub ss 1 | -1 </command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Sets the sample scattering sense. Allowed values are either 1 or
                                -1. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub silent 0 | 1 </command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Prints or sets the silent flag. If this is 0, the messages Driving
                                motor .. from .. to .. are suppressed.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub outofplane 0 | 1 </command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Prints or sets the outofplane flag. If this flag is 0, the
                                instrument will stay in the scattering plane and not move out of it.
                                This is here in order to protect those bloody magnets which cannot
                                be tilted.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub makeub</command><replaceable> r1 r2 </replaceable></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Calculate a new UB matrix from the current cell constants and the
                                entries r1 and r2 in the reflection list. r1 and r2 are integer
                                numbers. This command will not only print the new UB matrix but also
                                the results of various back and forth calculations performed with
                                the new UB matrix. This can be inspected in order to check the new
                                UB. WARNING: The calculation will go wrong if the scattering sense
                                at the sample has changed since the reflections used for the UB
                                matrix determination have been entered. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub listub </command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>prints the current UB matrix. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub calcang </command><replaceable>qh qk ql ei ef
                            </replaceable></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Will calculate new angles for the Q-E position specified. The
                                angles will be printed in the order: monochromator two theta, sample
                                rotation, sample two theta, lower tilt cradle, upper tilt cradle and
                                analyzer two theta. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub calcqe </command><replaceable>a2 a3 a4 sgu sgl a6
                            </replaceable></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Calculates and prints the Q-E position from the angles given: a2 =
                                monochromator two theta, a3 = sample rotation, a4 = sample tow
                                theta, sgu = upper tilt cradle, sgl = lower tilt cradle and a6 =
                                analyzer two theta. The Q-E position is printed in the sequence: qh,
                                qk, ql, ei, ef. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist></para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Virtual Motors</title>
            <para> The tasub module also installs the following virtual motors into SICS: ei, ki,
                qh, qk, ql, en, ef, kf and qm. All these motors can be used in SICS drive, run or
                scan commands like real motors. Driving them triggers a recalculation of angles and
                the drives the real motors to appropriate values. The virtual motors have a very
                limited command set (shown at the example of qh): <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>qh</command>
                        </term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The name of the motor alone will print its current position.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>qh</command>
                            <replaceable>target</replaceable>
                        </term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This will print the last requested target position for this
                                virtual motor. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist></para>
            <para> The virtual motor qm implements <emphasis role="b">powder mode</emphasis>. In
                this mode, only the sample two theta and energy motors will be driven, sample
                rotation and tilt cradles will be left at their respective positions. THis is
                commonly used to analyze the energy transfer of powder samples. </para>
            <para> There are other important command: <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub update </command></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This command will force a recalculation of the current Q-E
                                position for the virtual motors from angles. Normally tasub will
                                take care of this. However, if any of the angle motors are moved
                                directly or manualy, this command might be required. The SICS dr
                                wrapper command, however, even takes care of this. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist><variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub updatetargets</command>
                        </term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This command makes the QE targets macth the current position. This
                                is useful after initialization in the instrument.tcl file.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist></para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Internal Commands</title>
            <para> The tasub module supports some more commands which are used by SICS in order to
                restore the tasub configuration between instantiations of SICS. These commands are
                documented here for the sake of completeness: <variablelist>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub setub </command><replaceable>ub11 ub12 ub13 ub21 ub22
                                ub23 ub31 ub32 ub33 </replaceable></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Sets the UB matrix. Nine values are required. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub setnormal </command><replaceable>n1 n2 n3
                            </replaceable></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>This command sets the plane normal which is required in
                                calculations. Normally this plane normal is automatically generated
                                during the calculation of the UB matrix. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub settarget </command><replaceable> qh qk ql qm ki kf
                            </replaceable></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Sets the Q-E target. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub</command>
                            <replaceable> r1 qh qk ql a3 a4 sgu sgl ki kf </replaceable></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para/>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                        <term><command>tasub </command><replaceable>r2 qh qkl ql a3 a4 sgu sgl ki kf
                            </replaceable></term>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>These commands set the values for the two reflections used for
                                generating the UB matrix. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                </variablelist></para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
