<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <info><title>Histogram Control</title><author>
            <personname>Ferdi Franceschini</personname>
        </author>
        <date>2008-09-17 12:24</date>
    </info>
    <sect1>
        <title><command>histmem</command> command</title>
        <para>You can start and stop acquisitions and do limited configuration the histogram server
            with the histmem command. </para>
        <para>Note that histmem does not save data. You have to explicitly use the save command. </para>
        <para>The histogram memory server is a component that is separate from SICS. SICS currently
            exposes only a subset of the histogram server interface. In the future, Gumtree will
            provide an editor for the histogram server configuration files. </para>
        <para>For a simple experiment in beam monitor mode, where you want to histogram data until
            one million counts are counted in the beam monitor, from the command line you would</para>
        <para>
            <programlisting>
...
histmem mode MONITOR_1
histmem preset 1000000
histmem start
"wait until the histogram is finished"
save
</programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>For subsequent acquisitions where you want to do fast starts of the histogram server
            because you don't need to change configuration</para>
        <para>
            <programlisting>
histmem pause
do something in SICS like change the sample or temperature
histmem start
"wait until the histogram is finished"
save
        </programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>You must call the histmem command with one of the following subcommands</para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <command>histmem </command>
                    <command>start</command>
                    <option>block</option>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>will start an acquisition in the current mode</para>
                    <para>The option <option>block</option> prevents subsequent commands from being
                        processed until the histmem is finished. Used in scripts, when using the
                            <command>count</command> or <command>time</command> modes</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <command>histmem </command>
                    <command>stop</command>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>will stop the histogram memory if it is running in
                        <command>unlimited</command> mode that has been started without the
                            <option>block</option> option.</para>
                    <para>NOTE: If you are running in 'unlimited &amp; block' mode, count or time
                        modes, you must send an INT1712 1 to abort the acquistion or hit the
                        Interrupt button in Gumtree. </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <command>histmem </command>
                    <command>veto </command>
                    <option>enable/disable</option>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para><option>disable</option> will stop the histogram memory from counting and
                        not clear memory. It will have no effect on configuration. Use this command
                        if you need to pause a measurement without clearing the memory. </para>
                    <para><option>enable</option> will resume counting without clearing the memory.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <command>histmem </command>
                    <command>pause</command>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>if MULTIPLE_DATASETS=ENABLE mode (default - but check)</para>
                    <para>use pause instead of stop for a 'fast' start. Use this if you don't have
                        to change the histogram memory configuration. Clears histograms and
                        counters, but doesn't reinitialisation the histogram server. </para>
                    <para>if MULTIPLE_DATASETS=DISABLE mode</para>
                    <para>use pause instead of veto. Does not clear histograms and counters, does
                        not reinitialise the histogram server. Data is accumulated. </para>
                    <para>Note that the MULTIPLE_DATASETS mode is set in the SICS hmm configuration
                        files and/or on the histogram memory server. SICS does not report this
                        value. To view this value, you must look at the config tab on the histogram
                        server web client. </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <command>histmem </command>
                    <command>mode </command>
                    <replaceable>mode</replaceable>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Allowed <replaceable>mode </replaceable>one of:</para>
                    <para><command>MONITOR_n</command> (where n=1,2,3 ...). If you set the mode to
                        MONITOR_1 then the server will stop when MONITOR_1 reaches the
                            <command>preset</command> counts</para>
                    <para>
                        <command>time</command> will stop at the <command>preset</command> time
                        after <command>start</command></para>
                    <para>
                        <command>unlimited</command> will stop when it receives a <command>histmem
                            stop</command> or INT1712 1</para>
                    <para>
                        <command>count</command> will stop when the total histogram counts reaches
                            <command>preset</command> counts</para>
                    <para>
                        <command>frame</command> will stop when the <command>preset</command> number
                        of TOF (time of flight) frames. e.g. when there's no TOF, there is an
                        internal frame frequency which by default is 50Hz. So if you have a
                            <command>preset</command> of 1000 frames you will get a 20 second
                        acquisition</para>
                    <para>
                        <command>period</command> will stop when it reaches
                        <command>preset</command> number of periods. A histogram period contains
                        some number of frames averaged together - this is controlled by the BAT
                        (base address table) and its attributes. The mapping can be fairly complex
                        (e.g. time-averaged, time-history and stroboscopic acquisition) so there's
                        not always a simple relationship between number-of-periods acquired and the
                        DAQ time, but it can be worked out from the BAT setup</para>
                    <para><command>count_roi</command></para>
                    <para>Not supported. Will stop when the total histogram counts reaches
                            <command>preset</command> counts in a region of interest defined in the
                        histogram server configuration. </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <command>histmem preset </command>
                    <replaceable>val</replaceable>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>the acquisition will terminate after the <replaceable>val</replaceable>
                        period.  This is seconds if the mode is time, and counts if the mode is
                        count or MONITOR_n.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <command>histmem freq </command>
                    <replaceable>val</replaceable>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para><replaceable>val </replaceable> is the frame frequency (Hz)  for time
                        resolved data.  If you set a frequency of zero then this will default to
                        50Hz.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <command>histmem fsrce</command>
                    <replaceable>frame_source</replaceable>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Allow values of <replaceable>frame_source</replaceable> are:</para>
                    <para><option>EXTERNAL </option>(default) </para>
                    <para><option>INTERNAL </option>
                    </para>
                    <para>You can set this to <option>INTERNAL</option> if you don't have an
                        external frame signal</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <command>histmem </command>
                    <command>status</command>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para><warning>
                            <para>This doesn't report anything</para>
                        </warning> Started, Stopped, or Paused</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <command>histmem </command>
                    <command>loadconf</command>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>this uploads configuration tables (e.g. OAT for setting bins) to the
                        histogram memory</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><command>OAT_TABLE</command>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>with no arguments will print out <application>SICS</application>'s copy of
                        the OAT_TABLE</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><command>OAT_TABLE</command>
                    <option>-set X {</option>
                    <replaceable>bb0 bb1</replaceable>
                    <option>} Y {</option><replaceable>bb0 bb1</replaceable>
                    <option>} T </option>{<replaceable>bb0 bb1</replaceable>
                    <option>}</option></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>will generate a table starting at bin boundary
                        <replaceable>bb0</replaceable> with a spacing of (bb1-bb0) extrapolated to
                        the maximum bin boundary.  The numbers of channels are calculated
                        automatically.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><command>OAT_TABLE</command>
                    <option>-set X {</option>
                    <replaceable>bb0 bb1</replaceable>
                    <option>} Y {</option><replaceable>bb0 bb1</replaceable>
                    <option>} T </option>{<replaceable>bb0 bb1</replaceable>
                    <option>} NTC </option><replaceable>val1 </replaceable>
                    <option>NXC </option><replaceable>val2 </replaceable>
                    <option>NYC </option><replaceable>val3 </replaceable></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>this version sets the number of channels explicitly</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para><application>SICS</application> cannot read the current OAT_TABLE from the histogram
            server, the only way to make sure that <application>SICS</application> is in sync with
            the histogram memory is to use the <application>SICS</application>
            <command>OAT_TABLE</command>
            <option>-set </option> command to change your table and then to upload it to the
            histogram server with the <command>histmem loadconf </command>command</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Histogram memory object</title>
        <para>In most cases, the <command>histmem</command> command will be sufficient to configure
            and control an experiment. </para>
        <para>This section describes a richer level of configuration and control, using the SICS
            histogram memory object. The histogram memory object in SICS is used to set the
            configuration of the histogram memory server (described in detail in a later chapter),
            and to get the current histogram memory server configuration and data. Note that it is
            possible to for the histogram memory's configuration to be set independently from SICS
            e.g. through the histogram memory's web interface. Therefore, care must taken to ensure
            synchronisation between the SICS histogram memory object and the histogram memory
            server. </para>
        <para>SICS has seven histogram-memory objects as follows:</para>
        <para><command>hmm</command>
        </para>
        <para><command>hmm_xy</command>
        </para>
        <para><command>hmm_xt</command>
        </para>
        <para><command>hmm_yt</command>
        </para>
        <para><command>hmm_x</command>
        </para>
        <para><command>hmm_y</command>
        </para>
        <para><command>hmm_t</command>
        </para>
        <para>which you can use to fetch xyt, xy, xt, yt, x, y and t data. </para>
        <para>For simplicity, we will use <replaceable>hm</replaceable> to refer to any of the 7
            histogram memory objects. Make sure you use the one appropriate to your measurement. </para>
        <para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><replaceable>hm</replaceable><command> get 1</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>gets the current histogram memory data ie. 'live' data</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><replaceable>hm</replaceable><command> zipget 1</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>gets the current histogram memory data in binary zip form</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><replaceable>hm</replaceable><command> configure rank</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>gets the rank of the current histogram memory </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><replaceable>hm</replaceable><command> configure
                            dim</command><replaceable>n</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>gets the current histogram memory data in binary zip form</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
