<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0">
    <info><title>Interrupting SICS</title><author>
            <personname>Ferdi Franceschini</personname>
        </author>
        <date>2006-09-04 15:50</date>
        <bibliosource>The SICS programmers guide. converted to docbook using htlatex. converted to
            docbook5 by xslt in Oxygen. SINQ specific content removed</bibliosource>
    </info>
    <sect1>
        <title>Safety</title>
        <para>SICS is <emphasis role="bold">NOT</emphasis> a safety system! It will allow you to do
            tasks that may damage persons and the instruments. </para>
        <para>
        </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">DO</emphasis> use the <emphasis role="bold">STAR</emphasis>
            principle. <emphasis role="bold">STOP. THINK. ACT. REVIEW</emphasis></para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Familiarise</emphasis> yourself the location of the Emergency
            Stop buttons located near the cabin exit, or in several places within the instrument
            enclosure.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Familiarise</emphasis> yourself with the instrument and its safe
            operation. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">DO NOT</emphasis> do anything with SICS that may risk damage to
            persons or the instrument. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">DO NOT</emphasis> rely on these commands to stop motors or close
            shutters. If in any doubt, use the Emergency Stop button.</para>
        <para>The commands in this chapter may fail for a variety of reasons. <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SICS has crashed</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Your network connection to the SICS is blocked, due to network congestion
                        or failure</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The motor controller is no longer accepting connections or has a rogue
                        process running</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>stopexe command</title>
        <para>The <command>stopexe</command> command will stop drivable objects. It will NOT stop
            scans or batch files. For that you'll have to use an interrupt as found in the next
            section.</para>
        <para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>stopexe</command>
                        <replaceable>device</replaceable></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>interrupts a <command>drive</command> or <command>run</command>
                            command. In the case of motors, the motor will decelerate. It won't stop
                            immediately, as this can cause damage to the instrument </para>
                        <warning>
                            <para>This will not interrupt a scan e.g. <command>runscan</command>. </para>
                            <para>SICS will continue to accept commands from a client</para>
                        </warning>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term><command>stopexe all</command></term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>interrupts all devices. In the case of motors, the motor will
                            decelerate. It won't stop immediately, as this can cause damage to the
                            instrument </para>
                        <warning>
                            <para>This will not interrupt a scan e.g. <command>runscan</command>. </para>
                            <para>SICS will continue to accept commands from a client</para>
                        </warning>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <info>
            <title>Interrupting SICS</title>
        </info>
        <para>On occasion, you as the user, or a SICS object may come to the conclusion that an
            error is so bad that the measurement needs to be stopped. Clearly a means is needed to
            communicate this to upper level code. This means is setting an interrupt on the
            connection. The current active interrupt is located at the connection object (note for
            SICS programmers, this can be retrieved with SCGetInterrupt and set with SCSetInterrupt.
            Interrupt codes are defined in interrupt.h). These codes are ordered into a hierarchy</para>
        <para>
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term> INT1712 0 </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Continue. Everything is just fine. eContinue</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term> INT1712 1 </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Abort Operation. </para>
                    <para>Stop the current scan point or whatever is done, but do not stop
                        altogether. eAbortOperation</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term> INT1712 2 </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Abort Scan. </para>
                    <para>Abort the current scan, but continue processing of further commands in
                        buffers or command ﬁles. eAbortScan</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term> INT1712 3 </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Abort Batch. </para>
                    <para>Aborts everything, operations, scans and batch processing and leaves the
                        system ready to enter new commands. eAbortBatch</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term> INT1712 4 </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Halt System. </para>
                    <para>As eAbortBatch, but lock the system. eHaltSystem</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term> INT1712 5 </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Free System</para>
                    <para>Unlocks a system halted with eHaltSystem. eFreeSystem</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term> INT1712 6 </term>
                <listitem>
                    <warning>
                        <para>For internal usage only</para>
                    </warning>
                    <para>Makes the SICS server run down and exit. .</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>Higher level SICS objects may come to the conclusion that the error reported by lower
            level code is actually not that critical and clear any pending interrupts by setting the
            interrupt code to eContinue and thus consume the interrupt. </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
