<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title xml:id="analysisWindow">Data Analysis Window</title>

  <para>The Wombat Data Analysis Window is a customised graphic user interface
  for reducing raw data acquired by Wombat Instrument. It consists of 3 parts,
  File Manager, Algorithm Control and Plots. The data is in binary
  <emphasis>NeXus</emphasis> format and contains raw data acquired in a Scan
  done using the Experiment Window.</para>

  <para>To launch the analysis window, click on the
  <emphasis>Launch</emphasis> button, choose <emphasis>Analysis
  Window</emphasis> option.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Analysis Window</title>

    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="690"
                     fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/analysis_snapshot.PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <sect1>
    <title>Getting Started with Data Analysis</title>

    <para>A standard Wombat Data Analysis procedure includes the following
    steps: efficiency correction, geometry correction, 2θ integration and
    plotting. Please contact your instrument scientist for detail information
    about this procedure.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>File Manager</title>

      <para>On the top left part of the window, there is the <emphasis>File
      Manager</emphasis>, as shown in <xref linkend="file_source" />.</para>

      <figure xml:id="file_source">
        <title>File Manager</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/file_source.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Use button <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/add_item.gif"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> to pop up the file selection window. You can get
      the same window popped up by clicking on the drop down menu
      <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/common/view_menu.gif"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> and choose <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/add_files.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> option.</para>

      <figure xml:base="" xml:id="file_selection">
        <title>File Browser</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="360"
                       fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/file_browser.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>By default, the File Browser will use a filter to show all the
      files that have an extension name of '*.hdf'. You can also set the
      filter to show all files by setting the <emphasis>Files of
      type</emphasis> option to '*.*'. You can use the file browser window to
      select multiple files at the same time. Then click the
      <emphasis>Open</emphasis> button to confirm your selections. Once one or
      more files have been selected, the analysis application will pick the
      last file in the selections and run the analysis algorithm on it. The
      results of the analysis algorithm will be plotted in the Plot area of
      the Analysis Window.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="change_param">
      <title>Algorithm Control</title>

      <para><emphasis>Algorithm Control</emphasis> is located in the bottom
      left of the <emphasis>Analysis Window</emphasis>. Please read the
      following items to tune the algorithm. If you need detail information
      about the algorithm parameters, please read <xref
      linkend="sect_ap" />.</para>

      <sect3 xml:id="frame">
        <title>Frame</title>

        <para>A <emphasis role="italic">frame</emphasis> is defined as a
        single detector histogram which is a 2-dimensional array of neutron
        count data and has been taken at a single point in a multi-point scan.
        The number of frames equals the number of scan points.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Navigation Control</title>

        <para>By default when you first run the algorithm on a NeXus data
        file, it will pick the first <emphasis role="italic">frame</emphasis>
        of data to process. The correction result will show up in the
        uppermost Plot. It is a two-dimensional plot of the detector reading
        after efficiency correction and geometry correction, if you have
        enabled these corrections. If there is more than one frame in the data
        file, you need to use the widgets in <xref linkend="nav_control" /> to
        navigate through the frames.</para>

        <para>More detail can be found in <xref linkend="navigation" /></para>

        <figure xml:id="nav_control">
          <title>Navigation Control</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/navigate_group.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The <emphasis>jump to</emphasis> drop down list shows all
              the frame IDs. You can select to analyse on a frame by selecting
              an ID.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The <emphasis>step</emphasis> navigation buttons will help
              you to move forwards or backwards in the frame sequence.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The <emphasis>scan variable</emphasis> drop down list
              shows all the scan variable positions where each frame of data
              is taken. You can analyse on a frame by selecting its scan
              variable position.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Efficiency Correction Control</title>

        <para>You need to use an efficiency map file to correct the histogram
        data. The map can be either prepared in ahead of time or created at
        runtime. Please ask your instrument scientist for any prepared
        efficiency map files. To create an efficiency map file at runtime,
        please see <xref linkend="efficiencymap_section" />. Once you know the
        location of the efficiency files, you can use the widgets in <xref
        linkend="efficiency_group" /> to load the efficiency file. Enable
        efficiency correction by selecting the checkbox.</para>

        <figure xml:id="efficiency_group">
          <title>Efficiency Correction Control</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/efficiency_group.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>For more information on efficiency correction, please read <xref
        linkend="efficiencyCorrection" />.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Geometry Correction Control</title>

        <para>The geometry correction algorithm used in the analysis is to
        project a horizontal curved detector histogram onto a spherical
        surface. Please consult with your instrument scientist about whether
        you need to apply the geometry correction algorithm. To enable
        geometry correction, tick on the enable checkbox.<figure>
            <title>Geometry Correction Control</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/geometry_correction.PNG"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Plot</title>

      <para>The Plot area is in the right part of the window. There are three
      plots that show the results of the data reduction and analysis.</para>

      <para>To read more information about how to control Plot, for example
      zooming and panning, see <xref linkend="plotting" />.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Corrected Data</title>

        <para>The first Plot is a two-dimensional intensity plot that shows
        the corrected detector counts. If you have chosen to enable efficiency
        correction and geometry correction, it will plot the intensity data
        after these corrections. In the example of <xref
        linkend="correction_result_plot" />, both the vertical and horizontal
        axes are the physical dimensions of the detector. The colour of each
        pixel in the plot represents the neutron count reading in that
        location of the detector.</para>

        <figure xml:id="correction_result_plot">
          <title>Corrected Data Plot</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/2D_correction.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Integrated Counts</title>

        <para>The second plot is the vertically integrated detector counts as
        a curve. If you have applied a <emphasis>Region of
        Interests</emphasis> (ROI) in the intensity plot above, the algorithm
        will do the integration only in the 'region of interests' area.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Integrated Counts PlotSttt</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/integration_result.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Strips Plot</title>

        <para>The third Plot shows the aggregated strips plot. The vertical
        axis represents the scan variable, for example temperature. If you
        need more details about the result plots, please read <xref
        linkend="analysis_result" />.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Strips Plot</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/strips_plot.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>File Manager</title>

    <para>As shown in <xref linkend="file_source" />, users can manage the
    data source files in this <emphasis>File Manager</emphasis>. This section
    details how to use the file manager to select files for analysis.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Add Files</title>

      <para>You can use the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/add_item.gif"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button or drop down menu <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/add_files.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> to open a <emphasis>file selection
      window</emphasis> as shown in <xref linkend="file_selection" />. Once
      one or more files has been selected, they will be imported into the
      <emphasis>File Manager</emphasis>. The names and locations of these
      files will be shown. By default, the analysis algorithm will use the
      last file in the selection as the input file and automatically Analysed
      and Plotted.</para>

      <para>You can use this button to add one or many data files to the
      <emphasis>File Manager</emphasis>. However, only one file gets processed
      at a time and its result is plotted. The file that is processed gets
      highlighted, as shown in <xref linkend="files_example" />.</para>

      <figure xml:id="files_example">
        <title>File Manager</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/files_example.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Add Folder</title>

      <para>Use the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/add_dir.gif"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button or drop down menu <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/add_folder.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> to open a folder selection window as shown in
      <xref linkend="folder_selection" />. Once a folder has been selected,
      click on the <emphasis>OK</emphasis> button to confirm your selection.
      This will import all NeXus files in that folder to the <emphasis>File
      Manager</emphasis>. The last file in the selected folder will be
      automatically Analysed and Plotted.</para>

      <figure xml:id="folder_selection">
        <title>Folder Selection Window</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/select_folder.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="fileSelect">
      <title>Select an Input File</title>

      <para>To Analyse a file, select that file by a single click. The
      selected file is highlighted and Analysis starts. You can only select
      one file at a time, hence only one file is Analysed and Plotted. You can
      use the <emphasis>Arrow Up</emphasis> or <emphasis>Arrow Down</emphasis>
      keys on your keyboard to navigate through the files in the
      <emphasis>File Manager</emphasis>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Remove a File</title>

      <para>To remove a file from the File Manager, you need to select the
      file. Please read <xref linkend="fileSelect" /> on the detail. Use
      button <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/rem_item.gif"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> or drop down menu <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/remove_file.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>to remove the selected file. After removal, the
      file located immediately below it in the File Manager will be
      highlighted and Analysed and Plotted. If there is no file below, the
      file above will be selected, Analysed and Plotted. If after removal,
      there is no file in the File Manager, Plot will be empty. Since it does
      not support multi-selection, you cannot remove multiple files unless you
      choose to Remove All Files.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Remove All Files</title>

      <para>Use the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/rem_all_items.gif"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button or drop down menu <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/remove_folder.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> to remove all files in the <emphasis>File
      Manager</emphasis>. A confirmation window will pop up. If confirmed, all
      files are removed. Plot will be emptied.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Monitor Live Histogram Data</title>

      <para>If Gumtree-Wombat is connected to SICS it will monitor any new
      NeXus file created or modified by the SICS server. To learn about how to
      connect to SICS server, please read <xref linkend="installAndRun" />.
      When a new NeXus file is created, the File Manager will automatically
      read the file in. By default the files in the File Manager are sorted in
      a descending sequence. The new file usually has a larger numeric ID, so
      that it will be put on top of the file list in the File Manager. To
      Analyse and Plot the new file, simple click on it to select it.</para>

      <para>If the selected file is modified by SICS, Gumtree-Wombat will
      detect this and read the modified file. If the frame entry in the file
      gets changed, Gumtree will re-run Analysis and Plot on the new result.
      If there is a new frame entry appended to the file, Gumtree will pick up
      the entry and Analyse and Plot it.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sect_ap">
    <title>Algorithm Control</title>

    <para>In this section, you will find information about how to tune the
    analysis algorithms. <xref linkend="control_block" /> shows an overview of
    the <emphasis>Algorithm Control</emphasis>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="control_block">
      <title>Algorithm Control</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/control_block.PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <sect2>
      <title>How to Change a Parameter</title>

      <para>There are limited types of graphical widgets in
      <emphasis>Algorithm Control</emphasis>. They are checkbox, drop down
      list, file selection widget, navigation button and mask manager. Except
      for the navigation buttons, all changes to the above widgets need a
      confirmation click on the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/apply_button.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button. After the file is Analysed and Plotted,
      the <emphasis>Apply</emphasis> button is greyed out. Once a change is
      made to the control widgets, the <emphasis>Apply</emphasis> button is
      highlighted. A single clicking on this button will apply all the changes
      made and start Analysis and Plot. Navigation buttons are exceptions,
      they do not need confirmation.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="navigation">
      <title>Navigation Control</title>

      <para>There are three ways of navigating through the <xref
      linkend="frame" />frame sequence in the NeXus file.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use frame index</para>

          <para>The index of each frame will show up in the drop down list in
          <xref linkend="jump_to" />. Choose the index of a frame that you
          want to show by a single click in the drop down list.</para>

          <figure xml:id="jump_to">
            <title>Frame Index</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/jump_to.PNG"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use navigation buttons <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/nav_button.PNG"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>. You can navigate backwards or forwards along
          the frame sequence with these buttons.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use scan variable position</para>

          <para>The value of the scan variable for each frame will show up in
          the drop down list in <xref linkend="scan_variable" />. You can
          choose to show a frame by selecting the scan variable value of that
          frame.</para>

          <figure xml:id="scan_variable">
            <title>Scan Variable Values</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/scan_variable.PNG"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="efficiencyCorrection">
      <title>Efficiency Correction Control</title>

      <para>You need to use an efficiency map file to correct the histogram
      data. The map can be either prepared in ahead of time or created at
      runtime. Please ask your instrument scientist for any prepared
      efficiency map files. To create an efficiency map file at runtime,
      please see <xref linkend="efficiencymap_section" />. Once you know the
      location of the efficiency files, you can use the widgets in <xref
      linkend="efficiency_control" /> to load the efficiency file. Enable
      efficiency correction by selecting the checkbox.</para>

      <para>First, you need to select a folder where the efficiency maps are
      stored. Click on the folder selection button <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/select_file_button.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> to pop up a folder selection window. Once a
      folder is selected, its path gets inputted into the text box. And all
      efficiency map files will be listed in the file name drop down list. You
      can type the path of the file in the text box as well. Use the drop down
      list to select the correct efficiency map file.</para>

      <figure xml:id="efficiency_control">
        <title>Efficiency Correction Control</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/efficiency_group.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>You can enable or disable efficiency correction by changing
      selection of the checkbox. Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/apply_button.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button to apply the change.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="efficiencymap_section">
      <title>Create New Efficiency Map</title>

      <para>The efficiency maps used for efficiency correction can be
      different for different instrument environment. Sometimes the user needs
      to create an efficiency map file for a special scan. Gumtree provides a
      function to create an efficiency map on the fly. To open the window for
      creating effciency map, click on the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/efficiency_button.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button at the bottom of the control block. The
      window is shown in <xref linkend="make_efficiency" />. 
      	<figure
          xml:id="make_efficiency">
          <title>Efficiency Map Factory</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/make_efficiency.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>First, load a histogram data collection file in the <emphasis>long
      run</emphasis> parameter. The file is a common NEXUS data collected with
      the shutter open for an even distribution scattering. Next load a
      background data collection file in the <emphasis>bcg run</emphasis>
      parameter. The file is also a common NEXUS data collected with shutter
      closed. Then put a path for the new map file in the <emphasis>save
      to</emphasis> parameter. The new efficiency file is going to be saved to
      this path. By default it is a HDF file.</para>

      <para>After the setup, click on the <emphasis>Run</emphasis> button. The
      program starts to generate an efficiency map file. The progress bar
      displays the progress.</para>

      <para>Once the data gets created, there is a preview of the map
      displayed in right part of the window.</para>

      <para>If the path of the new file is under the folder which is used in
      the efficiency correction of the algorithm control, this new map will be
      automatically loaded to the drop down list of the efficiency control. To
      use the new efficiency map, simply select it from the list and click on
      <emphasis>Apply</emphasis> button. For example in <xref
      linkend="load_efficiency" />, <emphasis>new_map.hdf</emphasis> is a
      newly created file and can be used for correction.</para>

      <figure xml:id="load_efficiency">
        <title>Load New Efficiency Map</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/new_efficiencymap.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Geometry Correction Control</title>

      <para>The geometry correction algorithm used in the analysis is to
      project a flat detector histogram onto a spherical surface. Please
      consult with your instrument scientist about whether you need to apply
      the geometry correction algorithm. To enable geometry correction, simply
      click to select the checkbox in <xref linkend="geometry_control" />.
      Then click on <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/apply_button.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button to apply the change.</para>

      <figure xml:id="geometry_control">
        <title>Geometry Correction Control</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/geometry_correction.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="ROIMask">
      <title>Region of Interest and Masking Control</title>

      <para>In the analysis algorithm, you can put a series of mask as a
      single parameter to control selection of the detector histogram data.
      There are two types of masks, inclusive and exclusive. Inclusive masks
      are also called a <emphasis>Region of Interest</emphasis>, or ROI. If an
      ROI has been applied to the histogram data, only pixels included in the
      ROI will be considered in the analysis algorithm. Exclusive masks are
      called masks. If a mask has been applied to the histogram data, the
      pixels in the mask region will not be considered in the analysis
      algorithm.</para>

      <para>There are two ways of inputting ROI or masks into the algorithm.
      One is to draw regions on the two-dimensional intensity plot in the
      plotting area. The other is to use the <emphasis>Masking Properties
      Window</emphasis> to define regions.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To draw an ROI on the two-dimensional intensity plot, use
          <emphasis role="bold">ALT + Left Mouse Button</emphasis> combination
          to draw a rectilinear region on the plot. As shown in <xref
          linkend="ROI_plot" />, the colour of the ROI is green. To resize the
          ROI, move your mouse to the boarder of the region. The cursor
          becomes drag-able. You can drag the boarder to change the width or
          the height. To remove, move your mouse onto the ROI until the region
          gets focus. Push the <emphasis role="bold">DELETE</emphasis> key on
          your keyboard to remove.</para>

          <figure xml:id="ROI_plot">
            <title>ROI on 2D Plot</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/2D_mask.PNG"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To draw a mask on the two-dimensional intensity plot, use
          <emphasis role="bold">SHIFT + ALT + Left Mouse Button</emphasis>
          combination. The colour of the mask region is red. Other properties
          of the mask are the same as the ROI.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>You can draw as many ROI and masks on the intensity plot as you
      like. <xref linkend="mulit_mask" /> shows an example of drawing one ROI
      and two masks on the intensity plot.</para>

      <figure xml:id="mulit_mask">
        <title>Multiple ROI and Masks</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/3masks.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The other way of apply region selections is to define ROI and mask
      regions in the <emphasis>Masking Properties Window</emphasis>. To open
      this window, click on the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/select_file_button.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button in the algorithm control widget shown in
      <xref linkend="mask_control" />.</para>

      <figure xml:id="mask_control">
        <title>ROI and Mask Control</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/mask_control.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><xref linkend="mask_prop" /> shows an example of masking
      properties window.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To add a new mask, click on the <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/add_item.gif"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> button, a new mask item will show up in the
          <emphasis>Mask list</emphasis>. You can edit the position and size
          of the region by changing the coordinates of the mask in the
          <emphasis>Points</emphasis> widget. You can define as ROI or mask by
          switching between <emphasis>Inclusive</emphasis> and
          <emphasis>Exclusive</emphasis> options widget. You need to click on
          the <emphasis>Apply</emphasis> button to confirm any change.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To change the name of the region, simply type in the
          <emphasis>Name</emphasis> text box.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To remove a mask, click on the mask item. Then click on the
          <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/rem_item.gif"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> button.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To remove all masks, click on the <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/sourceView/rem_all_items.gif"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> button.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To save all the masks to a file, click on the
          <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/mask_save.gif"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> button. Pick a path and filename, then click
          on <emphasis>SAVE</emphasis>. All the masks drawn on the plot will
          be saved into the file in XML format.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>To load saved masks, click on the <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/mask_load.gif"></imagedata>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> button. Choose a file saved previously, then
          click <emphasis>OPEN</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure xml:id="mask_prop">
        <title>Mask Properties Window</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/mask_property.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The following logic describes how the regions define the
      selections of the histogram data.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If there is no ROI or mask region, all pixels in the detector
          histogram will be used.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If only masks exist, all pixels but the masked ones will be
          used.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If only ROI exist, only pixels in the ROI regions will be
          used.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If both ROI and masks exist, pixels in the ROI regions but not
          in the mask will be used.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Progress Bar</title>

      <para>The Progress Bar shows the progress of processing all frames in a
      single NeXus file, when you choose to run the algorithm on that
      file.<figure xml:id="batch_bar">
          <title>Export and Progress Bar</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/export_all.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Control Buttons</title>

      <para>There are 3 control buttons at the bottom of the algorithm control
      block, as shown in <xref linkend="control_buttons" />.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Efficiency</emphasis> button: use this button to
          open the window for creating new efficiency map files. For details
          about creating efficiency files, see <xref
          linkend="efficiencymap_section" />.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Apply</emphasis> button: after the algorithm
          finishes processing, this button gets disabled. If any parameter
          gets changed in the algorithm control block, this button is enabled.
          Press this button to apply the changes. This allows you to apply
          multiple changes at once.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Relaunch</emphasis> button: use this button to rerun
          the algorithm at any time.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure xml:id="control_buttons">
        <title>Control Buttons</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/control_buttons.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="analysis_result">
    <title>Plot</title>

    <para>There are three types of results for the Gumtree-Wombat data
    analysis, Corrected, Reduced and Analysed. In this section, we talk about
    these results.</para>

    <sect2 xml:id="correctionResult">
      <title>Corrected Data</title>

      <para>The first Plot shows the Corrected result. It is a two-dimensional
      detector histogram data plot. If you have chosen to enable efficiency
      correction and geometry correction, it will plot the intensity data
      after these corrections. <xref linkend="intensity_plot" /> shows this
      Plot. The vertical and horizontal axes are the physical dimensions of
      the detector. Units of the axes are <emphasis>mm</emphasis>. The
      horizontal axis is the 2θ values of the detector, in degrees.</para>

      <para>The colour of each pixel in the plot is coded by the number of
      neutron counts. The colour scale is located to the right of the plot.
      Readings from low to high coded by colors from dark to light. <figure
          xml:id="intensity_plot">
          <title>Corrected Data</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/2D_plot.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>To learn more information about the plot control, please read
      <xref linkend="plotting" />.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="reductionResult">
      <title>Integrated Counts</title>

      <para>The one-dimensional reduction result is located in the second
      plot. It is the integration of the corrected histogram data in vertical
      direction. The horizontal axis of the curve has been converted into 2θ
      values. <xref linkend="integration_plot" /> shows the integration result
      with a fitting curve. The integration result is plotted in Diamond
      markers and the fitting result is in a curved line. You can choose
      different marker shape for the plot. Please refer to <xref
      linkend="plotControl1D" />.</para>

      <figure xml:id="integration_plot">
        <title>Integrated Counts</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/integration_plot.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="analysisResult">
      <title>Strips Plot</title>

      <para>The analysis result of the algorithm will show up in the third
      plot in the plotting area. The vertical axis of the plot is the scan
      variables. For example, it can be temperature readings. <xref
      linkend="peak_positions" /> shows a plot with 43 strips aggregated in a
      strips plot, where vertical axis represents run numbers.</para>

      <figure xml:id="peak_positions">
        <title>Scan Data</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/integration_strips.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="save_scan">
      <title>Save Scan Data</title>

      <para>You can save different analysis results in multiple formats. The
      supported file formats are <emphasis>binary (HDF5),</emphasis>
      <emphasis>ASCII(3 columns)</emphasis>, and <emphasis>XML</emphasis>.
      There are different advantages in saving into different formats.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>HDF (Binary HDF5) format is a popular format in neutron
          scattering science. The NeXus data files created in Wombat
          experiments are also in HDF5 binary format. The data saved in HDF5
          format are compressed, which helps to save storage space. Such file
          that contains analysis result can be easily read back by Gumtree
          applications.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>XYSigma (ASCII, with 3 columns table) format is more
          human-readable. This format is only supported for exporting
          one-dimensional curve data. The 3 columns are the
          <emphasis>AXIS</emphasis>, the <emphasis>VALUE</emphasis>, and the
          <emphasis>ERROR</emphasis> respectively.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>XML format is available for both the two-dimensional result
          and one-dimensional curve result. The advantage of using this format
          is that it easily holds the metadata and it is human
          readable.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To choose to save the result in your local drive, click on the
      <emphasis>Export</emphasis> item in the plot menu, as shown in <xref
      linkend="export_result" />. Then choose the file format you want to
      save. A file selection window will show up. Choose the folder and give a
      name to the file, then click <emphasis>Save</emphasis>.</para>

      <figure xml:id="export_result">
        <title>Export Result Menu</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/export_menu.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="plotControl1D">
    <title>1D Plot Controls</title>

    <para>The following features are about features supported by a
    one-dimensional curve plot, for example the reduction result plot or the
    analysis result plot. To learn about the meaning of the 1D results, please
    read <xref linkend="reductionResult" />.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Plot Window Control</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Zoom</title>

        <para>To zoom in certain region of the 1D plot, simply <emphasis>push
        down the left mouse button and draw a rectilinear box from top left to
        bottom right</emphasis> on that region. You can use this action to
        zoom in up to possible zooming levels.</para>

        <para>To zoom out to the original level, <emphasis>push down the left
        mouse button and move it up or left</emphasis>. Another way to zoom
        out is to click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/refresh16x16.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button at the top left corner of the
        plot.</para>

        <para>You can also zoom in and out with the mouse wheel. Put the mouse
        over a point of interest. Then sroll up the mouse wheel to zoom in and
        scroll down to zoom out. If at the same time SHIFT key is pressed
        down, it will zoom in or out in a less progression rate.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Panning</title>

        <para>To pan current plot, press and hold CTRL key. Use the mouse to
        drag the plot in a direction.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Pick a point in the curve</title>

        <para>Single clicking on a point in the curve, it will provide a
        crossing at the point in blue colour. The crossing clearly tells the
        positions of the point. The detail values of the position will also
        show up in the status bar at the bottom of the plot.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Point Properties</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/point_properties.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Switch between logarithmic and linear axis</title>

        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/logarithm.gif"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to switch the vertical coordinate axis
        between logarithm axis and common axis. <xref
        linkend="logarithm_axis" /> shows an example with logarithm vertical
        axis in the plot.</para>

        <figure xml:id="logarithm_axis">
          <title>Logarithm Axis</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/logarithm.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Copy to clipboard</title>

        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/copy16x16.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to copy the current plot image into
        system clipboard. You can paste the image into common Windows imaging
        application such as <emphasis>MSPaint</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>MSOffice</emphasis> applications.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Save to image file</title>

        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/picture_save16x16.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to save the current plot to an image
        file in your file system. A <emphasis>Save As</emphasis> window will
        pop up for you to pick the folder and file name for the image file. It
        supports three image file formats: <emphasis>BMP</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>JPEG</emphasis> and <emphasis>PNG</emphasis>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Print the plot</title>

        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/printer16x16.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to print the current plot image. Two
        windows will pop up for you to setup the layout properties and to
        choose a printer.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="dataPropertiesControl1D">
      <title>Data</title>

      <para>Click on the <emphasis>Data</emphasis> item in the plot menu bar,
      a Data Control Block will show up in the left side of the plot. For
      example, <xref linkend="data_control_1D" /> shows the block of the
      integration result plot.</para>

      <figure xml:id="data_control_1D">
        <title>Data Control</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/1D_data_control.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The following features are supported in the Data Control
      Block.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Visible</title>

        <para>The first column of the data control area is visibility control.
        Select or deselect the check box in that column to show or hide the
        data.</para>

        <para>The one-dimensional curve data is called
        <emphasis>Pattern</emphasis> in Gumtree plotting space. Some time, the
        data fed to the plot can be a group of such one-dimensional data,
        which we call <emphasis>PatternSet</emphasis>. By default, all
        <emphasis>Patterns</emphasis> under the
        <emphasis>PatternSet</emphasis> will show up in the Visibility Control
        Area. Click on the button <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/folding_data.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> to fold the <emphasis>PatternSet</emphasis> so
        that it hides the <emphasis>Patterns</emphasis> within it. Click it
        again to unfold it. Deselect the visibility checkbox of the
        <emphasis>PatternSet</emphasis> will set all
        <emphasis>Patterns</emphasis> in it invisible.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Color</title>

        <para>Use the <emphasis>Colour</emphasis> column to change the colour
        of the curve shows in the plot. By default, the colors of the curve
        data are selected automatically from a rainbow colour series to be
        different from each other. You can change the colour of a single curve
        by clicking on the colour label in the <emphasis>Colour</emphasis>
        column. A <emphasis>Colour Selection Panel</emphasis> window will show
        up as in <xref linkend="color_panel" />. You can either choose a basic
        colour or click on the <emphasis>Define Custom Colors</emphasis> to
        generate a customised color. Click on OK to confirm the change.</para>

        <figure xml:id="color_panel">
          <title>Colour Selection Panel</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/color_panel.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Title</title>

        <para>By default, the title in the 1D plot uses the title of the data
        that put into the plot widget. So that you can control the title of
        the plot by changing the title of the data. To change the title,
        simply click on the current title of the data in the
        <emphasis>Title</emphasis> column, then type in a new text.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Change Title</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/change_title.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Marker</title>

        <para>You can change the marker shape of each curve in the plot. To
        change the marker shape, simply click on the drop down list in the
        <emphasis>Marker</emphasis> column and select one from the available
        marker shapes. <xref linkend="marker_table" /> shows the available
        marker shapes and their names.</para>

        <table xml:id="marker_table">
          <title>Available Marker Shapes</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec align="center" />

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Name</entry>

                <entry>Icon</entry>

                <entry>Style</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Line Only</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/line_only.PNG"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Diamond</entry>

                <entry>*</entry>

                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/diamond_shape.PNG"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Diagonal Cross</entry>

                <entry>x</entry>

                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/diagnal_cross.PNG"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Regular Cross</entry>

                <entry>+</entry>

                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/regular_cross.PNG"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Up Triangle</entry>

                <entry>^</entry>

                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/up_triangle.PNG"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Down Triangle</entry>

                <entry>v</entry>

                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/down_triangle.PNG"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Line Diamond</entry>

                <entry>-*</entry>

                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/line_diamond.PNG"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Line Diagonal Cross</entry>

                <entry>-x</entry>

                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/line_diagnal_cross.PNG"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Line Regular Cross</entry>

                <entry>-+</entry>

                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/line_regular_cross.PNG"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Line Up Triangle</entry>

                <entry>-^</entry>

                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/line_up_triangle.PNG"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Line Down Triangle</entry>

                <entry>-v</entry>

                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/line_down_triangle.PNG"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Linked</title>

        <para>To link the data with the algorithm means when the algorithm is
        processed again, new result data will overwrite the current data. This
        makes the plot updates automatically to the most recent result. By
        default this feature is enabled. To disable it, simply deselect the
        checkbox in the <emphasis>Linked</emphasis> column.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Metadata columns</title>

        <para>The metadata columns show the plot data information.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Reference</emphasis> column shows the ID of the
            algorithm that generates this plot.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Data type</emphasis> column shows the type of the
            data, such as <emphasis>Pattern</emphasis> or
            <emphasis>PatternSet</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Status</emphasis> column shows the status of the
            algorithm that generates this plot, for example,
            <emphasis>InProgress</emphasis>, <emphasis>Done</emphasis> or
            <emphasis>Error</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Timestamps</emphasis> column shows the time stamp
            of this plot data generation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="plotting">
    <title>2D Plot Controls</title>

    <para>The following features are about two-dimensional plots, e.g.
    Corrected Data plots (see <xref linkend="correctionResult" />)</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Plot Window Control</title>

      <para>The following features are supported by the two-dimensional
      window.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Zoom</title>

        <para>To zoom in certain region of the 2D plot, simply <emphasis>push
        down the left mouse button and draw a rectilinear box</emphasis> on
        that region.</para>

        <para>To zoom out use the key combination, <emphasis role="bold">CTRL
        + Z</emphasis> to zoom out to the next zoom level.</para>

        <para>To zoom out to the original level, use key combination,
        <emphasis role="bold">CTRL + SHIFT + Z</emphasis> or click on the
        <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/refresh16x16.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button at the top left corner of the
        plot.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Pan</title>

        <para>Pan is available if the plot has been zoomed. Push down the
        <emphasis role="bold">CTRL</emphasis> key, then drag the image to pan
        in any direction.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Show pixel properties</title>

        <para>Moving your mouse cursor to a pixel on the plot will get the
        pixel properties shown in the status bar. It tells you the horizontal
        axis value, the vertical axis value and the intensity reading on that
        pixel. It also tells you the zoom level.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Pixel Properties</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/pixel_properties.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Switch between linear and logarithmic colour scale</title>

        <para>Using logarithm colour scale can help to reveal lower intensity
        pixels in the plot. By default, the plot will use the common colour
        scale. Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/logarithm.gif"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to switch between common and logarithm
        colour scale. See <xref linkend="logarithm_scale" /> for the
        difference between common colour scale and logarithm colour
        scale.</para>

        <figure xml:id="logarithm_scale">
          <title>Linear and Logarithm Colour Scales</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/logarithm_scale.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Copy to clipboard</title>

        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/copy16x16.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to copy the current plot image into
        system clipboard. You can paste the image into common Windows imaging
        application such as <emphasis>MSPaint</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>MSOffice</emphasis> applications.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Save to image file</title>

        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/picture_save16x16.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to save the current plot to an image
        file in your file system. A <emphasis>Save As</emphasis> window will
        pop up for you to pick the folder and file name for the image file. It
        supports three image file formats: <emphasis>BMP</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>JPEG</emphasis> and <emphasis>PNG</emphasis>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Print the plot</title>

        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Plotting/printer16x16.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to print the current plot. Two windows
        will pop up for you to setup the layout properties and to choose a
        printer.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="dataPropertiesControl">
      <title>Data</title>

      <para>Click on the <emphasis>Data</emphasis> item in the plot menu bar,
      a <emphasis>Data Control</emphasis> will show up in the left side of the
      plot. For example, <xref linkend="data_control_2D" /> shows the block of
      the integration result plot.</para>

      <figure xml:id="data_control_2D">
        <title>Data Control</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/AlgorithmControl/2D_data_control.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The following features are supported in the <emphasis>Data Control
      Block</emphasis>.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Visible</title>

        <para>The first column of the <emphasis>Data Control Block</emphasis>
        is visibility control. Select or deselect the check box in that column
        to view or hide the data.</para>

        <para>A two-dimensional data is called <emphasis>Map</emphasis> in
        Gumtree plotting space. Some time, the data fed to the plot can be a
        group of such two-dimensional data, which we call
        <emphasis>MapSet</emphasis>. By default, all <emphasis>Maps</emphasis>
        under the <emphasis>MapSet</emphasis> will show up in the visibility
        control area. Click on the button <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/folding_data.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> to fold the <emphasis>MapSet</emphasis> so that
        it hides the <emphasis>Maps</emphasis> within it. Click it again to
        unfold it. Deselect the visibility checkbox of the
        <emphasis>MapSet</emphasis> will hide all <emphasis>Maps</emphasis> in
        it.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Color</title>

        <para>Use the <emphasis>Color</emphasis> column to change the colour
        scale of the two-dimensional plot. By default, the colour scale picked
        is Rainbow colour scale. All the supported colour scales are shown in
        <xref linkend="color_scales" />.</para>

        <figure xml:id="color_scales">
          <title>Colour Scales</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/color_scales.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>To change the colour scale, simply click on the current colour
        scale name in the <emphasis>Color</emphasis> column. A drop down list
        will show up as shown in <xref linkend="select_color_scale" />. Choose
        your selection to change the colour scale.</para>

        <figure xml:id="select_color_scale">
          <title>Select Colour Scale</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/color_scale.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Title</title>

        <para>By default, the title in the 2D plot uses the title of the data
        that put into the plot widget. So that you can control the title of
        the plot by changing the title of the data. To change the title,
        simply click on the current title of the data in the
        <emphasis>Title</emphasis> column, then type in a new text.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Change Title</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/change_title.PNG"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Linked</title>

        <para>To link the data with the algorithm means when the algorithm is
        processed again, the new result data will overwrite the current data.
        This makes the plot update automatically to the most recent result. By
        default this feature is enabled. To disable it, simply deselect the
        checkbox in the <emphasis>Linked</emphasis> column.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Meta data columns</title>

        <para>The metadata columns in the data control area shows the plot
        data information.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Reference</emphasis> column shows the ID of the
            algorithm that generates this plot.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Data type</emphasis> column shows the type of the
            data, such as <emphasis>Map</emphasis> or
            <emphasis>MapSet</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Status</emphasis> column shows the status of the
            algorithm that generates this plot, for example,
            <emphasis>InProgress</emphasis>, <emphasis>Done</emphasis> or
            <emphasis>Error</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Timestamps</emphasis> column shows the time stamp
            of this plot data gets generated.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>View</title>

      <para>Click on the <emphasis>View</emphasis> item in the plot menu bar
      will show up the View Properties Control, as shown in <xref
      linkend="view_control" />.</para>

      <figure xml:id="view_control">
        <title>View Properties Control</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/view_control.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>View mode - Intensity</para>

          <para>Use this to choose the Plot data. It is supported to put
          multiple plot data into the 2D plot widget. They can be in single
          <emphasis>Map</emphasis> data, or enclosed in
          <emphasis>MapSet</emphasis> data (for more information, please see
          <xref linkend="dataPropertiesControl" />). All available 2D Maps are
          available in the Intensity drop down list as shown in the above
          figure. Click on the drop down list to choose a Map data to
          plot.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Flip X-Axis</para>

          <para>Use the checkbox of <emphasis>Flip X-Axis</emphasis> to flip
          the plot and axis horizontally.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Statistic Data</para>

          <para>Click on the <emphasis>Statistic Data</emphasis> checkbox to
          show statistic properties of the plot data. The statistic properties
          will show up in the right part of the plot in table mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Title mode - Generated</para>

          <para>By default it will use the title of the plot data as the plot
          title. You can choose the <emphasis>Custom</emphasis> radio button
          to overwrite the title. Simply type new text in the text box will
          change the title of the plot.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Fitting</title>

      <para>Under construction</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Mask</title>

      <para>To enable of disable the Mask feature, use the <emphasis>Mask
      Control</emphasis>. Click on the <emphasis>Mask</emphasis> item in the
      plot menu bar. The Mask Control will show up as shown in <xref
      linkend="masking_control" />.</para>

      <figure xml:id="masking_control">
        <title>Mask Control</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/mask_control.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>By default the Mask feature is enabled. To disable this feature,
      click on the Mask enabled checkbox. If disabled, the Plot will not show
      any mask or ROI. The drop down list in the Mask Control provides options
      of which algorithm parameter will take the mask. To learn more
      information about how to use masks in an algorithm, please read <xref
      linkend="ROIMask" />.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Export</title>

      <para>Use this menu to save data. See <xref
      xlink:href="#save_scan" /></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Navigation Bar</title>

      <para>If there are more than one dataset in the Plot, you can use the
      navigation buttons <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="wombat.ui.images/analysis/Kakadu/nav_bar.PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> in the Plot menu bar to jump forwards or
      backwards in the sequence. If there is only one dataset, this feature is
      disabled.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- nxi: hide unfinished section
  <sect1>
    <title>Analysis Troubleshooting</title>
    <para>Under construction</para>
  </sect1>
   -->
</chapter>
