<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title xml:id="analysisWindow">Data Analysis Window</title>
  <para>The Kowari Data Analysis Window is a customised graphic user interface for reducing raw data
    acquired by Kowari. It consists of 4 parts, File Manager, Batch Data Processing and Export,
    Algorithm Control and Plot. The data is in binary <emphasis>NeXus</emphasis> format and contains
    raw data acquired in a Scan done using the Experiment Window.</para>
  <para>To launch the analysis window, click on the <emphasis>Launch</emphasis> button, choose
      <emphasis>Perspective</emphasis> option, then choose <emphasis>Kowari Data Analysis</emphasis>
    option.</para>
  <figure>
    <title>Analysis Window</title>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentwidth="640" fileref="kowari.ui.images/analysis_snapshot.PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>
  <sect1>
    <title>Getting Started with Data Analysis</title>
    <para>A standard Kowari Data Analysis procedure includes the following steps: efficiency
      correction, geometry correction, 2θ integration and curve fitting. Please contact your
      instrument scientist for detail information about this procedure.</para>
    <sect2>
      <title>File Manager</title>
      <para>On the top left part of the window, there is the <emphasis>File Manager</emphasis>, as
        shown in <xref linkend="file_source"/>.</para>
      <figure xml:id="file_source">
        <title>File Manager</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/file_source.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Use button <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/add_item.gif"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> to pop up the file selection window. You can get the same window popped
        up by clicking on the drop down menu <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/RPC/drop_down.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> and choose <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/add_files.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> option.</para>
      <figure xml:base="" xml:id="file_selection">
        <title>File Browser</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentwidth="480" fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/file_browser.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>By default, the File Browser will use a filter to show all the files that have an
        extension name of '*.hdf'. You can also set the filter to show all files by setting the
          <emphasis>Files of type</emphasis> option to '*.*'. You can use the file browser window to
        select multiple files at the same time. Then click the <emphasis>Open</emphasis> button to
        confirm your selections. Once one or more files have been selected, the analysis application
        will pick the last file in the selections and run the analysis algorithm on it. The results
        of the analysis algorithm will be plotted in the Plot area of the Analysis Window.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title xml:id="change_param">Algorithm Control</title>
      <para><emphasis>Algorithm Control</emphasis> is located in the bottom left of the Analysis
        Window. Please read the following items to tune the algorithms. If you need detail
        information about the algorithm parameters, please read <xref linkend="sect_ap"/>.</para>
      <sect3>
        <title xml:id="frame">Frame</title>
        <para>A <emphasis role="italic">frame</emphasis> is defined as a single detector histogram
          which is a 2-dimensional array of neutron count data and has been taken at a single point
          in a multi-point scan. The number of frames equals the number of scan points.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Navigation Control</title>
        <para>By default when you first run the algorithm on a NeXus data file, it will pick the
          first <emphasis role="italic"><xref linkend="frame"/>frame</emphasis> of data to process.
          The correction result will show up in the uppermost Plot. It is a two-dimensional plot of
          the detector reading after efficiency correction and geometry correction, if you have
          enabled these corrections. If there is more than one frame in the data file, you need to
          use the widgets in <xref linkend="nav_control"/> to navigate through the frames.</para>
        <para>More detail can be found in <xref linkend="navigation"/></para>
        <figure xml:id="nav_control">
          <title>Navigation Control</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/navigate_group.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The <emphasis>jump to</emphasis> drop down list shows all the frame IDs. You can
                select to analyse on a frame by selecting an ID.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The <emphasis>step</emphasis> navigation buttons will help you to move forwards
                or backwards in the frame sequence.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The <emphasis>scan variable</emphasis> drop down list shows all the scan
                variable positions where each frame of data is taken. You can analyse on a frame by
                selecting its scan variable position.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Efficiency Correction Control</title>
        <para>The instrument scientist will prepare the efficiency map of the detector ahead of
          time. Please ask your instrument scientist for the location of this file. Once you know
          where to find this file, you can use the widgets in <xref linkend="efficiency_group"/> to
          load the efficiency file. Enable efficiency correction by selecting the checkbox.</para>
        <figure xml:id="efficiency_group">
          <title>Efficiency Correction Control</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/efficiency_group.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>For more information on efficiency correction, please read <xref
            linkend="efficiencyCorrection"/>.</para>
      </sect3>
      <!-- nxi: hide temporarily
      <sect3>
        <title>Choose Analysis Result</title>
        <para>By default the algorithm result shown in the third Plot is the intensity integration
          result. You can use the widgets in <xref linkend="result_control"/> to change to view
          different analysis results. Please read more information about analysis result plots in
            <xref linkend="analysis_result"/>.</para>
        <figure xml:id="result_control">
          <title>Result Selection</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/result_control.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      -->
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Plot</title>
      <para>The Plot area is the right part of the window. There are three plots that show the
        results of the data reduction and analysis.</para>
      <para>To read more information about how to control Plot, for example zoom see <xref
          linkend="plotting"/>.</para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Corrected Data</title>
        <para>The first Plot is a two-dimensional intensity plot that shows the corrected detector
          counts. If you have chosen to enable efficiency correction and geometry correction, it
          will plot the intensity data after these corrections. In the example of <xref
            linkend="correction_result_plot"/>, both the vertical and horizontal axes are the
          physical dimensions of the detector. The colour of each pixel in the plot represents the
          neutron count reading in that location of the detector.</para>
        <figure xml:id="correction_result_plot">
          <title>Corrected Data</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/2D_correction.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Integrated Counts</title>
        <para>The second Plot consists of two plots. The vertically integrated detector counts are
          shown as points, and a fit to these points is shown as a curve. If you have applied a
            <emphasis>Region of Interests</emphasis> (ROI) in the intensity plot above, the
          algorithm will do the integration only in the masked area.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Integrated Counts</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/integration_result.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Scan Data</title>
        <para>The third Plot shows the aggregated scan data. By default it shows the
            <emphasis>intensity integration of the whole detector vs scan variable</emphasis> plot.
          <!--  nxi: hide temporarily
          You can use the control widgets shown in <xref linkend="result_control"/> to show other
          plots. For example plot the <emphasis>fitting peak vs scan variable</emphasis> plot. 
          -->
          If you need more details about the result plots, please read <xref linkend="analysis_result"
          />.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Scan Data</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/intensity_result.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>File Manager</title>
    <para>As shown in <xref linkend="file_source"/>, users can manage the data source files in this
        <emphasis>File Manager</emphasis>. This section details how to use the file manager to
      select files for analysis.</para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Add Files</title>
      <para>You can use the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/add_item.gif"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button or drop down menu <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/add_files.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> to open a <emphasis>file selection window</emphasis> as shown in <xref
          linkend="file_selection"/>. Once one or more files has been selected, they will be
        imported into the <emphasis>File Manager</emphasis>. The names and locations of these files
        will be shown. By default, the analysis algorithm will use the last file in the selection as
        the input file and automatically Analysed and Plotted.</para>
      <para>You can use this button to add one or many data files to the <emphasis>File
        Manager</emphasis>. However, only one file gets processed at a time and its result is
        plotted. The file that is processed gets highlighted, as shown in <xref
          linkend="files_example"/>.</para>
      <figure xml:id="files_example">
        <title>File Manager</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/files_example.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Add Folder</title>
      <para>Use the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/add_dir.gif"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button or drop down menu <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/add_folder.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> to open a folder selection window as shown in <xref
          linkend="folder_selection"/>. Once a folder has been selected, click on the
        <emphasis>OK</emphasis> button to confirm your selection. This will import all NeXus files
        in that folder to the <emphasis>File Manager</emphasis>. The last file in the selected
        folder will be automatically Analysed and Plotted.</para>
      <figure xml:id="folder_selection">
        <title>Folder Selection Window</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/select_folder.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title xml:id="fileSelect">Select an Input File</title>
      <para>To Analyse a file, select that file by a single click. The selected file is highlighted
        and Analysis starts. You can only select one file at a time, hence only one file is Analysed
        and Plotted. You can use the <emphasis>Arrow Up</emphasis> or <emphasis>Arrow
        Down</emphasis> keys on your keyboard to navigate through the files in the <emphasis>File
          Manager</emphasis>.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Remove a File</title>
      <para>To remove a file from the File Manager, you need to select the file. Please read <xref
          linkend="fileSelect"/> on the detail. Use button <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/rem_item.gif"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> or drop down menu <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/remove_file.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>to remove the selected file. After removal, the file located immediately
        below it in the File Manager will be highlighted and Analysed and Plotted. If there is no
        file below, the file above will be selected, Analysed and Plotted. If after removal, there
        is no file in the File Manager, Plot will be empty. Since it does not support
        multi-selection, you cannot remove multiple files unless you choose to Remove All
      Files.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Remove All Files</title>
      <para>Use the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/rem_all_items.gif"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button or drop down menu <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/remove_folder.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> to remove all files in the <emphasis>File Manager</emphasis>. A
        confirmation window will pop up. If confirmed, all files are removed. Plot will be
      emptied.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Monitor Live Histogram Data</title>
      <para>If Gumtree-Kowari is connected to SICS it will monitor any new NeXus file created or
        modified by the SICS server. To learn about how to connect to SICS server, please read <xref
          linkend="installAndRun"/>. When a new NeXus file is created, the File Manager will
        automatically read the file in. By default the files in the File Manager are sorted in a
        descending sequence. The new file usually has a larger numeric ID, so that it will be put on
        top of the file list in the File Manager. To Analyse and Plot the new file, simple click on
        it to select it.</para>
      <para>If the selected file is modified by SICS, Gumtree-Kowari will detect this and read the
        modified file. If the frame entry in the file gets changed, Gumtree will re-run Analysis and
        Plot on the new result. If there is a new frame entry appended to the file, Gumtree will
        pick up the entry and Analyse and Plot it.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Batch Data Processing and Export</title>
    <para>The Export All (batch data processing and save) button and a progress bar are located in
      the center left of the window, as shown in <xref linkend="batch_bar"/>.</para>
    <figure xml:id="batch_bar">
      <title>Export and Progress Bar</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/export_all.PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <sect2>
      <title>Batch Processing</title>
      <para>You can reduce and export all files loaded into the File Manager. Using Export All, the
        NeXus data files are read sequentially and processed with the reduction algorithm. The
        one-dimensional vertically integrated result curves are saved into
        <emphasis>XYSigma</emphasis> ASCII files. For each NeXus file, there is one
          <emphasis>XYSigma</emphasis> file created. There is several lines of header information in
        the file to show the metadata. Each curve also follows a couple of header lines to tell the
        scan variable information.</para>
      <para>To do batch processing, click on the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/export_button.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button. A <emphasis>Folder Selection Window</emphasis> will pop up.
        After you confirm your selection, Gumtree will begin the process. The name of the exported
        files are the same as the NeXus files e.g. KWR1234567 but with an appended suffix and file
        extension. If efficiency correction is enabled in the <emphasis>Algorithm
        Control</emphasis>, it will append '_e' to the export file name. If geometry correction is
        enabled, it will append '_g' to the export file name. If there is a mask region applied, it
        will append the vertical boundary information of the region to the file name, e.g.
        '_-137.0_125.0' means vertical region from -137.0 mm to 125.0 mm. The extension will be
        *.xyd. An example of the file name is: KWR0003415_eg_-137.0_125.0.xyd, with efficiency
        correction, geometry correction and mask enabled. Data can also be saved one file at a time.
        See <xref xlink:href="#save_scan"/></para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Progress Bar</title>
      <para>The progress bar represents the processing progress in two different modes.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>File process mode. The Progress Bar shows the progress of processing all frames in a
            single NeXus file, when you choose to run the algorithm for a single file.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>File export mode. The Progress bar shows the progress of exporting all files in the
            File Manager.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="sect_ap">
    <title>Algorithm Control</title>
    <para>In this section, you will find information about how to tune the analysis algorithms.
        <xref linkend="control_block"/> shows an overview of the <emphasis>Algorithm
      Control</emphasis>.</para>
    <figure xml:id="control_block">
      <title>Algorithm Control</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/control_block.PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <sect2>
      <title>How to Change a Parameter</title>
      <para>There are limited types of graphical widgets in <emphasis>Algorithm Control</emphasis>.
        They are checkbox, drop down list, file selection widget, navigation button and mask
        manager. Except for the navigation buttons, all changes to the above widgets need a
        confirmation click on the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/apply_button.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button. After the file is Analysed and Plotted, the
        <emphasis>Apply</emphasis> button is greyed out. Once a change is made to the control
        widgets, the <emphasis>Apply</emphasis> button is highlighted. A single clicking on this
        button will apply all the changes made and start Analysis and Plot. Navigation buttons are
        exceptions, they do not need confirmation.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Use Corrected Data</title>
      <para>In the NeXus file, the detector count data are accompanied with corrected data, which is
        corrected for count binning artefacts generated by the detector and its electronics. The
        corrected data is produced by the histogram server which uses dithering to balance counts in
        adjacent wires on the detector. By default, uncorrected data is Analysed and Plotted.
        Consult with your instrument scientist if you need to use the corrected data.</para>
      <para>To use the wire corrected data, click to select the checkbox <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/use_correction.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="navigation">
      <title>Navigation Control</title>
      <para>There are three ways of navigating through the <xref linkend="frame"/>frame sequence in
        the NeXus file.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use frame index</para>
          <para>The index of each frame will show up in the drop down list in <xref
              linkend="jump_to"/>. Choose the index of a frame that you want to show by a single
            click in the drop down list.</para>
          <figure xml:id="jump_to">
            <title>Frame Index</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/jump_to.PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use navigation buttons <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/nav_button.PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject>. You can navigate backwards or forwards along the frame sequence
            with these buttons.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use scan variable position</para>
          <para>The value of the scan variable for each frame will show up in the drop down list in
              <xref linkend="scan_variable"/>. You can choose to show a frame by selecting the scan
            variable value of that frame.</para>
          <figure xml:id="scan_variable">
            <title>Scan Variable Values</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/scan_variable.PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="efficiencyCorrection">
      <title>Efficiency Correction Control</title>
      <para>Usually the instrument scientist will prepare the efficiency map of the detector before
        you arrive and put it in your proposal directory. Please consult with your instrument
        scientist for the details of this file. To use the efficiency map file, you can use the
        widgets shown in <xref linkend="efficiency_control"/> to load it. Click on the file
        selection button <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/select_file_button.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>, to pop up a file selection window. Once the efficiency map file is
        selected, its path gets inputted into the text box. You can type the path of the file in the
        text box as well.</para>
      <figure xml:id="efficiency_control">
        <title>Efficiency Correction Control</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/efficiency_control.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>You can enable or disable efficiency correction by changing selection of the checkbox.
        Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/apply_button.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button to apply the change.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Geometry Correction Control</title>
      <para>The geometry correction algorithm used in the analysis is to project a flat detector
        histogram onto a spherical surface. Please consult with your instrument scientist if you
        need to apply the geometry correction algorithm. To enable geometry correction, simply click
        to select the checkbox in <xref linkend="geometry_control"/>. Then click on
          <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/apply_button.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button to apply the change.</para>
      <figure xml:id="geometry_control">
        <title>Geometry Correction Control</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/geometry_correction.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title xml:id="ROIMask">Region of Interest and Masking Control</title>
      <para>In the analysis algorithm, you can put a series of mask as a single parameter to control
        selection of the detector histogram data. There are two types of masks, inclusive and
        exclusive. Inclusive masks are also called a <emphasis>Region of Interest</emphasis>, or
        ROI. If an ROI has been applied to the histogram data, only pixels included in the ROI will
        be considered in the analysis algorithm. Exclusive masks are called masks. If a mask has
        been applied to the histogram data, the pixels in the mask region will not be considered in
        the analysis algorithm.</para>
      <para>There are two ways of inputting ROI or masks into the algorithm. One is to draw regions
        on the two-dimensional intensity plot in the plotting area. The other is to use the
          <emphasis>Masking Properties Window</emphasis> to define regions.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To draw an ROI on the two-dimensional intensity plot, use <emphasis role="bold">ALT
              + Left Mouse Button</emphasis> combination to draw a rectilinear region on the plot.
            As shown in <xref linkend="ROI_plot"/>, the colour of the ROI is green. To resize the
            ROI, move your mouse to the boarder of the region. The cursor becomes drag-able. You can
            drag the boarder to change the width or the height. To remove, move your mouse onto the
            ROI until the region gets focus. Push the <emphasis role="bold">DELETE</emphasis> key on
            your keyboard to remove.</para>
          <figure xml:id="ROI_plot">
            <title>ROI on 2D Plot</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/2D_mask.PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To draw a mask on the two-dimensional intensity plot, use <emphasis role="bold"
              >SHIFT + ALT + Left Mouse Button</emphasis> combination. The colour of the mask region
            is red. Other properties of the mask are the same as the ROI.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>You can draw as many ROI and masks on the intensity plot as you like. <xref
          linkend="mulit_mask"/> shows an example of drawing one ROI and two masks on the intensity
        plot.</para>
      <figure xml:id="mulit_mask">
        <title>Multiple ROI and Masks</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/3masks.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The other way of apply region selections is to define ROI and mask regions in the
          <emphasis>Masking Properties Window</emphasis>. To open this window, click on the
          <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/select_file_button.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> button in the algorithm control widget shown in <xref
          linkend="mask_control"/>.</para>
      <figure xml:id="mask_control">
        <title>ROI and Mask Control</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/mask_control.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para><xref linkend="mask_prop"/> shows an example of masking properties window.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To add a new mask, click on the <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/add_item.gif"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> button, a new mask item will show up in the <emphasis>Mask
            list</emphasis>. You can edit the position and size of the region by changing the
            coordinates of the mask in the <emphasis>Points</emphasis> widget. You can define as ROI
            or mask by switching between <emphasis>Inclusive</emphasis> and
            <emphasis>Exclusive</emphasis> options widget. You need to click on the
            <emphasis>Apply</emphasis> button to confirm any change.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To change the name of the region, simply type in the <emphasis>Name</emphasis> text
            box.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To remove a mask, click on the mask item. Then click on the <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/rem_item.gif"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> button.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To remove all masks, click on the <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/SourceView/rem_all_items.gif"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> button.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To save all the masks to a file, click on the <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/mask_save.gif"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> button. Pick a path and filename, then click on
            <emphasis>SAVE</emphasis>. All the masks drawn on the plot will be saved into the file
            in XML format.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To load saved masks, click on the <inlinemediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/mask_load.gif"/>
              </imageobject>
            </inlinemediaobject> button. Choose a file saved previously, then click
            <emphasis>OPEN</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <figure xml:id="mask_prop">
        <title>Mask Properties Window</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/mask_property.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The following logic describes how the regions define the selections of the histogram
        data.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If there is no ROI or mask region, all pixels in the detector histogram will be
            used.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If only masks exist, all pixels but the masked ones will be used.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If only ROI exist, only pixels in the ROI regions will be used.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If both ROI and masks exist, pixels in the ROI regions but not in the mask will be
            used.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
    <!-- nxi: hide temporarily
    <sect2 xml:id="chooseResult">
      <title>Choose Analysis Result</title>
      <para>By default the algorithm result shown in the third Plot is the integrated intensity of
        each frame. You can use the widgets in <xref linkend="result_option"/> to change the view of
        different analysis results. This change will affect the curve shown in the third Plot.
          <figure xml:id="result_option">
          <title>Result Selection Control</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/result_control.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose <emphasis>Intensity</emphasis> shows the integrated counts over the region of
            interest of each frame vs scan variable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose <emphasis>mean</emphasis> shows the fitted peak position of the frame vs scan
            variable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose <emphasis>Chi2</emphasis> shows the fitting quality Chi square values of the
            frame vs scan variable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose <emphasis>amplitude</emphasis> shows the fitted amplitude values of the frame
            vs scan variable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose <emphasis>sigma</emphasis> shows the fitted sigma values of the frame vs scan
            variable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose <emphasis>area</emphasis> shows the fitted Gaussian curve area of the frame
            (calculated from sigma and amplitude) vs scan variable.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    -->
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title xml:id="analysis_result">Plot</title>
    <para>There are three types of results for the Gumtree-Kowari data analysis, Corrected, Reduced
      and Analysed. In this section, we talk about these results.</para>
    <sect2>
      <title xml:id="correctionResult">Corrected Data</title>
      <para>The first Plot shows the Corrected result. It is a two-dimensional detector histogram
        data plot. If you have chosen to enable efficiency correction and geometry correction, it
        will plot the intensity data after these corrections. <xref linkend="intensity_plot"/> shows
        this Plot. The vertical and horizontal axes are the physical dimensions of the detector.
        Units of the axes are <emphasis>mm</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>The colour of each pixel in the plot is coded by the number of neutron counts. The
        colour scale is located to the right of the plot. Readings from low to high coded by colors
        from dark to light. <figure xml:id="intensity_plot">
          <title>Corrected Data</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/2D_plot.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
      <para>To learn more information about the plot control, please read <xref linkend="plotting"
        />.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title xml:id="reductionResult">Integrated Counts</title>
      <para>The one-dimensional reduction result is located in the second plot. It is the
        integration of the corrected histogram data in vertical direction. The horizontal axis of
        the curve has been converted into 2θ values. <xref linkend="integration_plot"/> shows the
        integration result with a fitting curve. The integration result is plotted in Diamond
        markers and the fitting result is in a curved line. You can choose different marker shape
        for the plot. Please refer to <xref linkend="plotControl1D"/>.</para>
      <figure xml:id="integration_plot">
        <title>Integrated Counts</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/integration_plot.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title xml:id="analysisResult">Scan Data</title>
      <para>The analysis result of the algorithm will show up in the third plot in the plotting
        area. 
        <!-- 
        You can choose to show different analysis result in the algorithm control widget (see
          <xref linkend="chooseResult"/> for details about selecting result). When you select a
        different result, the different curve will show up.
        --> 
        The horizontal axis of the plot is
        always the scan variables. For example, <xref linkend="peak_positions"/> shows the peak
        positions of the fitting of the frames vs the scan variable values.</para>
      <figure xml:id="peak_positions">
        <title>Scan Data</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/fitting_peaks.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>All features in the 1D curve plot are supported by this Plot. However there are
          additional features for this plot.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Jump to a frame</para>
            <para><emphasis>Double click on a point</emphasis> to pick the histogram frame that has
              a scan variable value as your selection. The algorithm will pick the frame as input
              and start processing. As a result, in the first plot of the plotting area, it will
              show the correction result of that frame. In the second plot, it will show the
              reduction result of that frame.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 xml:id="save_scan">
      <title>Save Scan Data</title>
      <para>You can save different analysis results in multiple formats. The supported file formats
        are <emphasis>binary (HDF5),</emphasis>
        <emphasis>ASCII(3 columns)</emphasis>, and <emphasis>XML</emphasis>. There are different
        advantages in saving into different formats.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>HDF (Binary HDF5) format is a popular format in neutron scattering science. The
            NeXus data files created in Kowari experiments are also in HDF5 binary format. The data
            saved in HDF5 format are compressed, which helps to save storage space. Such file that
            contains analysis result can be easily read back by Gumtree applications.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>XYSigma (ASCII, with 3 columns table) format is more human-readable. This format is
            only supported for exporting one-dimensional curve data. The 3 columns are the
              <emphasis>AXIS</emphasis>, the <emphasis>VALUE</emphasis>, and the
            <emphasis>ERROR</emphasis> respectively.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>XML format is available for both the two-dimensional result and one-dimensional
            curve result. The advantage of using this format is that it easily holds the metadata
            and it is human readable.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>To choose to save the result in your local drive, click on the
        <emphasis>Export</emphasis> item in the plot menu, as shown in <xref linkend="export_result"
        />. Then choose the file format you want to save. A file selection window will show up.
        Choose the folder and give a name to the file, then click <emphasis>Save</emphasis>.</para>
      <figure xml:id="export_result">
        <title>Export Result Menu</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/export_menu.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title xml:id="plotControl1D">1D Plot Controls</title>
    <para>The following features are about features supported by a one-dimensional curve plot, for
      example the reduction result plot or the analysis result plot. To learn about the meaning of
      the 1D results, please read <xref linkend="reductionResult"/> and <xref
        linkend="analysisResult"/>.</para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Plot Window Control</title>
      <sect3>
        <title>Zoom</title>
        <para>To zoom in certain region of the 1D plot, simply <emphasis>push down the left mouse
            button and draw a rectilinear box from top left to bottom right</emphasis> on that
          region. You can use this action to zoom in up to possible zooming levels.</para>
        <para>To zoom out to the original level, <emphasis>push down the left mouse button and move
            it up or left</emphasis>. Another way to zoom out is to click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/refresh16x16.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button at the top left corner of the plot.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Pick a point in the curve</title>
        <para>Single click on a point in the curve, it will provide a crossing at the point in blue
          colour. The crossing clearly tells the positions of the point. The detail values of the
          position will also show up in the status bar at the bottom of the plot.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Point Properties</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/point_properties.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Switch between logarithmic and linear axis</title>
        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/logarithm.gif"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to switch the vertical coordinate axis between logarithm axis
          and common axis. <xref linkend="logarithm_axis"/> shows an example with logarithm vertical
          axis in the plot.</para>
        <figure xml:id="logarithm_axis">
          <title>Logarithm Axis</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/logarithm.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Copy to clipboard</title>
        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/copy16x16.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to copy the current plot image into system clipboard. You can
          paste the image into common Windows imaging application such as
          <emphasis>MSPaint</emphasis> and <emphasis>MSOffice</emphasis> applications.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Save to image file</title>
        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/picture_save16x16.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to save the current plot to an image file in your file system.
          A <emphasis>Save As</emphasis> window will pop up for you to pick the folder and file name
          for the image file. It supports three image file formats: <emphasis>BMP</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>JPEG</emphasis> and <emphasis>PNG</emphasis>.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Print the plot</title>
        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/printer16x16.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to print the current plot image. Two windows will pop up for
          you to setup the layout properties and to choose a printer.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title xml:id="dataPropertiesControl1D">Data</title>
      <para>Click on the <emphasis>Data</emphasis> item in the plot menu bar, a Data Control Block
        will show up in the left side of the plot. For example, <xref linkend="data_control_1D"/>
        shows the block of the integration result plot.</para>
      <figure xml:id="data_control_1D">
        <title>Data Control</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/1D_data_control.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The following features are supported in the Data Control Block.</para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Visible</title>
        <para>The first column of the data control area is visibility control. Select or deselect
          the check box in that column to show or hide the data.</para>
        <para>The one-dimensional curve data is called <emphasis>Pattern</emphasis> in Gumtree
          plotting space. Some time, the data fed to the plot can be a group of such one-dimensional
          data, which we call <emphasis>PatternSet</emphasis>. By default, all
          <emphasis>Patterns</emphasis> under the <emphasis>PatternSet</emphasis> will show up in
          the Visibility Control Area. Click on the button <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/folding_data.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> to fold the <emphasis>PatternSet</emphasis> so that it hides the
            <emphasis>Patterns</emphasis> within it. Click it again to unfold it. Deselect the
          visibility checkbox of the <emphasis>PatternSet</emphasis> will set all
          <emphasis>Patterns</emphasis> in it invisible.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Color</title>
        <para>Use the <emphasis>Colour</emphasis> column to change the colour of the curve shows in
          the plot. By default, the colors of the curve data are selected automatically from a
          rainbow colour series to be different from each other. You can change the colour of a
          single curve by clicking on the colour label in the <emphasis>Colour</emphasis> column. A
            <emphasis>Colour Selection Panel</emphasis> window will show up as in <xref
            linkend="color_panel"/>. You can either choose a basic colour or click on the
            <emphasis>Define Custom Colors</emphasis> to generate a customised color. Click on OK to
          confirm the change.</para>
        <figure xml:id="color_panel">
          <title>Colour Selection Panel</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/color_panel.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Title</title>
        <para>By default, the title in the 1D plot uses the title of the data that put into the plot
          widget. So that you can control the title of the plot by changing the title of the data.
          To change the title, simply click on the current title of the data in the
          <emphasis>Title</emphasis> column, then type in a new text.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Change Title</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/change_title.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Marker</title>
        <para>You can change the marker shape of each curve in the plot. To change the marker shape,
          simply click on the drop down list in the <emphasis>Marker</emphasis> column and select
          one from the available marker shapes. <xref linkend="marker_table"/> shows the available
          marker shapes and their names.</para>
        <table xml:id="marker_table">
          <title>Available Marker Shapes</title>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec align="center"/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Name</entry>
                <entry>Icon</entry>
                <entry>Style</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Line Only</entry>
                <entry>-</entry>
                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/line_only.PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Diamond</entry>
                <entry>*</entry>
                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/diamond_shape.PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Diagonal Cross</entry>
                <entry>x</entry>
                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/diagnal_cross.PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Regular Cross</entry>
                <entry>+</entry>
                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/regular_cross.PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Up Triangle</entry>
                <entry>^</entry>
                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/up_triangle.PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Down Triangle</entry>
                <entry>v</entry>
                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/down_triangle.PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Line Diamond</entry>
                <entry>-*</entry>
                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/line_diamond.PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Line Diagonal Cross</entry>
                <entry>-x</entry>
                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/line_diagnal_cross.PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Line Regular Cross</entry>
                <entry>-+</entry>
                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/line_regular_cross.PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Line Up Triangle</entry>
                <entry>-^</entry>
                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/line_up_triangle.PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Line Down Triangle</entry>
                <entry>-v</entry>
                <entry><inlinemediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/line_down_triangle.PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                  </inlinemediaobject></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Linked</title>
        <para>To link the data with the algorithm means when the algorithm is processed again, new
          result data will overwrite the current data. This makes the plot updates automatically to
          the most recent result. By default this feature is enabled. To disable it, simply deselect
          the checkbox in the <emphasis>Linked</emphasis> column.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Metadata columns</title>
        <para>The metadata columns show the plot data information.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Reference</emphasis> column shows the ID of the algorithm that generates
              this plot.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Data type</emphasis> column shows the type of the data, such as
                <emphasis>Pattern</emphasis> or <emphasis>PatternSet</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Status</emphasis> column shows the status of the algorithm that
              generates this plot, for example, <emphasis>InProgress</emphasis>,
              <emphasis>Done</emphasis> or <emphasis>Error</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Timestamps</emphasis> column shows the time stamp of this plot data
              generation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title xml:id="plotting">2D Plot Controls</title>
    <para>The following features are about two-dimensional plots, e.g. Corrected Data plots (see
        <xref linkend="correctionResult"/>)</para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Plot Window Control</title>
      <para>The following features are supported by the two-dimensional window</para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Zoom</title>
        <para>To zoom in certain region of the 2D plot, simply <emphasis>push down the left mouse
            button and draw a rectilinear box</emphasis> on that region.</para>
        <para>To zoom out use the key combination, <emphasis role="bold">CTRL + Z</emphasis> to zoom
          out to the next zoom level.</para>
        <para>To zoom out to the original level, use key combination, <emphasis role="bold">CTRL +
            SHIFT + Z</emphasis> or click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/refresh16x16.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button at the top left corner of the plot.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Pan</title>
        <para>Pan is available if the plot has been zoomed. Push down the <emphasis role="bold"
          >CTRL</emphasis> key, then drag the image to pan in any direction.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Show pixel properties</title>
        <para>Moving your mouse cursor to a pixel on the plot will get the pixel properties shown in
          the status bar. It tells you the horizontal axis value, the vertical axis value and the
          intensity reading on that pixel. It also tells you the zoom level.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Pixel Properties</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/pixel_properties.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Switch between linear and logarithmic colour scale</title>
        <para>Using logarithm colour scale can help to reveal lower intensity pixels in the plot. By
          default, the plot will use the common colour scale. Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/logarithm.gif"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to switch between common and logarithm colour scale. See <xref
            linkend="logarithm_scale"/> for the difference between common colour scale and logarithm
          colour scale.</para>
        <figure xml:id="logarithm_scale">
          <title>Linear and Logarithm Colour Scales</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/logarithm_scale.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Copy to clipboard</title>
        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/copy16x16.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to copy the current plot image into system clipboard. You can
          paste the image into common Windows imaging application such as
          <emphasis>MSPaint</emphasis> and <emphasis>MSOffice</emphasis> applications.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Save to image file</title>
        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/picture_save16x16.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to save the current plot to an image file in your file system.
          A <emphasis>Save As</emphasis> window will pop up for you to pick the folder and file name
          for the image file. It supports three image file formats: <emphasis>BMP</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>JPEG</emphasis> and <emphasis>PNG</emphasis>.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Print the plot</title>
        <para>Click on the <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Plotting/printer16x16.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> button to print the current plot. Two windows will pop up for you to
          setup the layout properties and to choose a printer.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title xml:id="dataPropertiesControl">Data</title>
      <para>Click on the <emphasis>Data</emphasis> item in the plot menu bar, a <emphasis>Data
          Control</emphasis> will show up in the left side of the plot. For example, <xref
          linkend="data_control_2D"/> shows the block of the integration result plot.</para>
      <figure xml:id="data_control_2D">
        <title>Data Control</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/AlgorithmControl/2D_data_control.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The following features are supported in the <emphasis>Data Control Block</emphasis>.</para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Visible</title>
        <para>The first column of the <emphasis>Data Control Block</emphasis> is visibility control.
          Select or deselect the check box in that column to view or hide the data.</para>
        <para>A two-dimensional data is called <emphasis>Map</emphasis> in Gumtree plotting space.
          Some time, the data fed to the plot can be a group of such two-dimensional data, which we
          call <emphasis>MapSet</emphasis>. By default, all <emphasis>Maps</emphasis> under the
            <emphasis>MapSet</emphasis> will show up in the visibility control area. Click on the
          button <inlinemediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/folding_data.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject> to fold the <emphasis>MapSet</emphasis> so that it hides the
            <emphasis>Maps</emphasis> within it. Click it again to unfold it. Deselect the
          visibility checkbox of the <emphasis>MapSet</emphasis> will hide all
          <emphasis>Maps</emphasis> in it.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Color</title>
        <para>Use the <emphasis>Color</emphasis> column to change the colour scale of the
          two-dimensional plot. By default, the colour scale picked is Rainbow colour scale. All the
          supported colour scales are shown in <xref linkend="color_scales"/>.</para>
        <figure xml:id="color_scales">
          <title>Colour Scales</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/color_scales.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>To change the colour scale, simply click on the current colour scale name in the
            <emphasis>Color</emphasis> column. A drop down list will show up as shown in <xref
            linkend="select_color_scale"/>. Choose your selection to change the colour scale.</para>
        <figure xml:id="select_color_scale">
          <title>Select Colour Scale</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/color_scale.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Title</title>
        <para>By default, the title in the 2D plot uses the title of the data that put into the plot
          widget. So that you can control the title of the plot by changing the title of the data.
          To change the title, simply click on the current title of the data in the
          <emphasis>Title</emphasis> column, then type in a new text.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Change Title</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/change_title.PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Linked</title>
        <para>To link the data with the algorithm means when the algorithm is processed again, the
          new result data will overwrite the current data. This makes the plot update automatically
          to the most recent result. By default this feature is enabled. To disable it, simply
          deselect the checkbox in the <emphasis>Linked</emphasis> column.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Meta data columns</title>
        <para>The metadata columns in the data control area shows the plot data information.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Reference</emphasis> column shows the ID of the algorithm that generates
              this plot.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Data type</emphasis> column shows the type of the data, such as
                <emphasis>Map</emphasis> or <emphasis>MapSet</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Status</emphasis> column shows the status of the algorithm that
              generates this plot, for example, <emphasis>InProgress</emphasis>,
              <emphasis>Done</emphasis> or <emphasis>Error</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Timestamps</emphasis> column shows the time stamp of this plot data gets
              generated.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>View</title>
      <para>Click on the <emphasis>View</emphasis> item in the plot menu bar will show up the View
        Properties Control, as shown in <xref linkend="view_control"/>.</para>
      <figure xml:id="view_control">
        <title>View Properties Control</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/view_control.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>View mode - Intensity</para>
          <para>Use this to choose the Plot data. It is supported to put multiple plot data into the
            2D plot widget. They can be in single <emphasis>Map</emphasis> data, or enclosed in
              <emphasis>MapSet</emphasis> data (for more information, please see <xref
              linkend="dataPropertiesControl"/>). All available 2D Maps are available in the
            Intensity drop down list as shown in the above figure. Click on the drop down list to
            choose a Map data to plot.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Flip X-Axis</para>
          <para>Use the checkbox of <emphasis>Flip X-Axis</emphasis> to flip the plot and axis
            horizontally.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Statistic Data</para>
          <para>Click on the <emphasis>Statistic Data</emphasis> checkbox to show statistic
            properties of the plot data. The statistic properties will show up in the right part of
            the plot in table mode.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Title mode - Generated</para>
          <para>By default it will use the title of the plot data as the plot title. You can choose
            the <emphasis>Custom</emphasis> radio button to overwrite the title. Simply type new
            text in the text box will change the title of the plot.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Fitting</title>
      <para>Under construction</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Mask</title>
      <para>To enable of disable the Mask feature, use the <emphasis>Mask Control</emphasis>. Click
        on the <emphasis>Mask</emphasis> item in the plot menu bar. The Mask Control will show up as
        shown in <xref linkend="masking_control"/>.</para>
      <figure xml:id="masking_control">
        <title>Mask Control</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/mask_control.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>By default the Mask feature is enabled. To disable this feature, click on the Mask
        enabled checkbox. If disabled, the Plot will not show any mask or ROI. The drop down list in
        the Mask Control provides options of which algorithm parameter will take the mask. To learn
        more information about how to use masks in an algorithm, please read <xref linkend="ROIMask"
        />.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Export</title>
      <para>Use this menu to save data. See <xref xlink:href="#save_scan"/></para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Navigation Bar</title>
      <para>If there are more than one dataset in the Plot, you can use the navigation buttons
          <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="kowari.ui.images/Kakadu/nav_bar.PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject> in the Plot menu bar to jump forwards or backwards in the sequence. If
        there is only one dataset, this feature is disabled.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <!-- nxi: hide unfinished section
  <sect1>
    <title>Analysis Troubleshooting</title>
    <para>Under construction</para>
  </sect1>
   -->
</chapter>
